Aisling Lilian Rayne

Centre for Sustainability, University of Otago & Te Pūnaha Matatini Centre for Research Excellence

D+64 27 864 3230

♀ Lincoln, Aotearoa New Zealand

■ a.l.rayne@outlook.co.nz

y @aisrayne

github.com/rayne95

3 Google Scholar

R⁶ ResearchGate

Introduction

As an emerging social scientist and tangata Tiriti, my research aims to understand and enable transformative change in complex systems. Since my rural upbringing to post-PhD, I have been deeply curious about our diverse relationships with more-than-human nature. My PhD extended traditional conservation genomics into an interdisciplinary space through community partnerships, including the centring of mātauranga-ā-iwi-ā-hapū and Indigenous data sovereignty. Since then, I have been studying diversity, equity, and inclusion in the research system using mixed methods (e.g., questionnaires, interview, reflexive thematic analysis and social network analysis) through a lens of care ethics. Along with my co-leadership roles in New Zealand's Biological Heritage National Science Challenge and Te Pūnaha Matatini Whānau, I look forward to bringing these diverse experiences to bear in future collaborations at the people-environment interface.

Professional experience

CENTRE FOR SUSTAINABILITY, UNIVERSITY OF OTAGO & TE PŪNAHA MATATINI Research Fellow (0.8 FTE. End date: 31 July 2022) • The Kindness in Science Project

Research Tenow (0.0 1 1E. End date: 31 July 2022) • The Kindness in Science 1 toject

New Zealand's Biological Heritage National Science Challenge

2022-present Co-lead • Ngā Pī Ka Rere (Early Career Pou)

Independent Researcher (o.2 FTE) • Impact Pou & Freshwater Strategic Investment Plan

University of Canterbury

Research Associate (Conservation Genomics) • School of Biological Sciences

 $_{2017-2020}$ Lab Demonstrator • School of Biological Sciences

Teaching Assistant • School of Educational Studies and Leadership

Education

2022-present

PHD in Biological Sciences, University of Canterbury

BSc(Hons, 1st Class) in Biological Sciences, University of Canterbury

BSc in Ecology, University of Canterbury

Services & affiliations

2022-present Secretary, **Te Pūnaha Matatini Whānau**, Te Pūnaha Matatini 2022-present Advisor, **Kā Ara Tīpuna (VMCF)**, Te Rūnanga o Ngāi Tahu

₂₀₂₁-present Technical Advisor, **Te Pātaka a Tahu (MABx)**, Te Rūnanga o Ngāi Tahu

2020-present Member, Technical Advisory Group on Regenerative Farming Practices, MPI

2020-2021	Member, High Quality Genomes and Population Genomics, Genomics Aotearoa
2017-2020	Executive Member, Student Volunteer Army , University of Canterbury
	Λ 1
	Awards
2020	Bioheritage COVID-19 Extension Scholarship
2018	Roper Doctoral Scholarship for top-ranked domestic applicant in Science at UC
2017	UC Annual Biology Conference Best BSc/BSc(Hons) Presentation
2017	Todd Foundation Award for Excellence
2016	University of Canterbury Senior Scholarship
2016	LIC Patrick Shannon Scholarship
2016	Canterbury Branch New Zealand Federation of Graduate Women Trust Award
2015	UC Pilgrim Prize
2014	UC Emerging Leaders Development Program
2014	UC Undergraduate Entrance Scholarship
2013	Orion Selwyn District Centenary Educational Trust Scholarship
2013	Darfield High School Parent Teacher Student Association Prize for Dux
	Research grants (contributing researcher)
2022	Investigator Seed Funding, Te Pūnaha Matatini (\$58K awarded to TE Steeves)
2021-2023	Vision Mātauranga Capability Fund (Connect), Ministry of Business, Innovation and
	Employment (\$250K awarded to Te Rūnanga o Ngāi Tahu)
2021-2023	Māori Agribusiness Extension (MABx) Phase I, Ministry for Primary Industries (\$60K awarded to
	Te Rūnanga o Ngāi Tahu)
2019-2020	Research Linkages Seeding Grant, College of Science, UC (\$20K awarded to TE Steeves)
2017	Data Deficient Research Grant, Department of Conservation (\$3.8K awarded to TE Steeves)
	Publications & talks
	1 diffications & tarks
	Peer-reviewed articles
In Press	Forsdick N, Adams CI, Alexander A, Clark AC, Collier-Robinson L, Cubrinovska I, Croll Dowgray
	M, Dowle E, Duntsch L, Galla SJ, Howell L, Magid M, Rayne A, Verry AJF, Wold J, Steeves TE.
	Current applications and future promise of genetic/genomic data for conservation in an Aotearoa
	New Zealand context. In Press at Science for Conservation. [DOI]
2022	Rayne A, Blair S, Dale M, Flack B, Hollows J, Moraga R, Parata RN, Rupene M, Tamati-Elliffe P,
	Wehi PM, Wylie MJ, Steeves TE. Weaving place-based knowledge for culturally significant species
	in the age of genomics: Looking to the past to navigate the future. <i>Evol Appl</i> 15:751–772. [DOI] [PDF]
2020	Rayne A, Byrnes G, Collier-Robinson L, Hollows J, McIntosh A, Ramsden M, Rupene M,
	Tamati-Elliffe P, Thoms C, Steeves TE. Centring Indigenous knowledge systems to re-imagine

Collier-Robinson L, Rayne A, Rupene M, Thoms C, Steeves TE. Embedding Indigenous principles

in genomic research of culturally significant species. NZ $\mathcal{J}Ecol$ 43:3389. [DOI] [PDF]

conservation translocations. People & Nat 2:512–526. [doi] [pdf]

2019

PRE-PRINTS & PAPERS IN PREPARATION/REVIEW/REVISION

Parker KA, Ewen JG, Weiser EL, Rayne A, Steeves TE, Seddon PJ, ... Armstrong DP. Contemporary conservation translocations are foundational to Predator-Free aspirations in Aotearoa New Zealand: a review. EcoEvoRxiv (In Review for NZ J Ecol). [DOI] Cox B, Rayne A, Sharp E, Walker L, Steeves TE. Allyship and self-determination: Caring-with in In Prep academic spaces. Finlay-Smits S, McRae K, Rayne A, Palmer S, Warburton H. Reflecting on the Challenge: impacts In Prep of being involved in New Zealand's Biological Heritage National Science Challenge. In preparation for submission to 7 R Soc NZ Rayne A, Cox B, Sharp E, Walker L, Wehi C, Steeves TE. Kindness in science: I do not think it In Prep means what you think it means. In preparation for submission to eLife Rayne A, Pawlick, Steeves TE. Caring-with in peer review. In preparation for submission to NZES In Prep Hot Topics Sharp E, Cox B, Rayne A. The 'Good Kiwi' and the 'Good Climate Citizen': Dairy consumption, In Prep national identity and complex climate-related values in Aotearoa New Zealand. In preparation for submission to J Rural Stud Other forms of dissemination Article for the Spinoff Brilliant assholes and the kindness of aunties In Prep Contributed to Te Pūnaha Matatini submission on Te Ara Paerangi Building an ethical, agile, 2022 collaborative research system [HTML] Interview for RNZ's Our Changing World podcast Collaborating to move freshwater species [HTML] 2021 Invited article for Wiley Centring Indigenous ways of knowing to enhance resilience [HTML] 2021 The Conversation When rehoming wildlife, Indigenous leadership delivers the best results [HTML] 2020 Bioheritage blog How can we best use genomics to enhance conservation translocations? [HTML] UC annual Research Report Securing sustainable kai: a conservation genomics approach [PDF] 2019 Featured in UCMe campaign for the University of Canterbury [HTML] 2019 Contributed to expert commentary with A/Prof Tammy Steeves on new biodiversity strategy Te 2019 Koiroa o Te Koiora [HTML] Bioheritage blog Cutting-edge technology to help making akai species [HTML] 2019 SELECTED TALKS Allyship and self-determination: Caring-with in academic spaces. Feminist Geographies 2022. 2022 Boulder, Colorado, U.S.A (co-presented virtually with Dr Emma Sharp & Bethany Cox. Pre-recorded for June 17) Ngā Pī Ka Rere: Early Careers taking flight. Crazy & Ambitious 3 (co-presented virtually with Dr 2022 Kathryn McRae, Dr Helen Warburton & Symon Palmer) Invited virtual keynote Looking to the past to navigate the future: Weaving place-based knowledge for culturally significant species in the age of genomics. MAPNET, Plant & Food Research Invited talk Weaving ways of knowing to enhance biocultural resilience in a mahinga kai 2021 species-at-risk. Waterways. Ōtautahi Christchurch Invited virtual talk on Applied Genomics & NZ Indigenous Engagement, Australasian Genomic 2021

Technologies Association. Sydney, Australia [WATCH ONLINE]

Invited virtual talk Enhancing biocultural resilience in a mahinga kai species-at-risk. IAGLR. 2021 Windsor, Canada Re-imagining conservation translocations through Two-Eyed Seeing. Hawai'i Conservation 2020 Alliance. Honolulu, Hawai'i (presented virtually) Have your kēkēwai and eat it too: Bridging species and ecosystem recovery. NZ Ecological Society 2019 Conference. Lincoln New knowledge, old legislation: An integrative approach for enhancing resilience in Aotearoa New 2019 Zealand's threatened freshwater biota. ICCB. Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. Underwater, out of mind? A call for integrative legislation reform, Crazy & Ambitious 2. 2019 Wellington. Critical first steps toward enhancing resilience in two threatened freshwater endemics, UNVEIL 2018 Symposium. Flathead Lake, Montana, U.S.A. (co-presented with Levi Collier-Robinson).